to a keep this church alive six years ago, seven years ago,
and b continually breathe the life of Christ into each and every
one of us and this body. So, I'm honored to serve with
you and walk alongside of you and you have continually greatly impacted
my life. It's like every time just was it th Friday we
were standing out back talking a little bit and I'm just like
this is exactly what I need to hear. I wish Shnie was
standing here right now cuz she needs it too. So, uh, no
matter if we're working on something together or sweating out back together
or just sitting in the office talking, there is, uh, there's always
just a Rama word that's ministering to me and my family and
each and every one of you as well as you encounter him.
So, I'm appreciative of you. Thank you, Pastor John.
[applause]
>> The honor is all mine, honestly.
Amazing. many amazing people we have in this church. So many of
you guys are just dearly, dearly loved by the Lord. Just precious
saints. I'm so honored to walk with you all. Thank you for
that glowing uh announcement there. Yes. Sorry. I uh
I was thinking about the word this morning and had like this
last minute thought and was like trying to put it in there.
But anyways, well, we had a a great time last week. It
wasn't too hot. We didn't we didn't overheat. Um at least I didn't.
I don't think Allan any anybody get the opportunity to dunk Allan
last week. No, we let all the kids Oh, Matthew got to
dunk Allen. Then Judah did, too. Was that fun? Good job. Good
job.
>> Yeah, we Now you know where to send the chiropractic bill.
Oh, well, praise God. Lord, we love you. Thank you, Lord. Lord,
as we worshiped you this morning, it it's such a wonderful thing
to be in your presence, Lord, to taste of of your spirit
and to be reminded, God, of your faithfulness over the years, Lord.
Um, we just bless you. We we acknowledge, God, that you are
perfect, Jesus. You are perfect in all of your ways. >> Lord, there's
there's none like you, Lord. I I remember the day that I
met you and everything changed. And then I remember as I discovered
you, God, um more and more through your word, I discovered just
perfect humanity.
So, we're grateful, God. I'm grateful, Lord, for the way that you
have loved me back to health, for investing in my life, for
investing in my future. And Lord, we just so adore you and
look forward to all that you're going to do this morning. So,
Holy Spirit, come. We welcome you. We just invite you to rest
on us and to open our hearts and our minds and our
eyes to see Jesus, to see the father uh in in such
a greater light this morning. Amen. >> Amen.
So, I don't know about you guys, um, but I've I've never
I'm going to pick on Liam Niss for a few minutes. [laughter]
It seems like a lot of the the movies that he has
done in the last decade or so are are movies where uh
his daughter was brutally tortured or something and and kidnapped and tortured
and it's all these vengeance type movies for a kid being abducted
or whatever. And um I was thinking about that because it pertains
to what I feel like the Lord has us to talk about
today. But um when I was growing in my faith and as
a young man and learning uh to cooperate with this program with
this uh transformational process uh that the Lord is currently still working
on me, transforming me into the image of Jesus. uh and the
work of the spirit, how many of you know will sometimes surprise
you at some of the things that he highlights or some of
the things that he brings to the surface and says, "Hey, this
is the season we're going to work on this. We're going to
redeem this." And and um I I I remember as a young father,
I really was aware of um just the strong sense of justice
that I've always carried even when I wasn't walking with the Lord.
And I was careful about things that I consume, things that I
would watch because of the effect it would have of what it
stirred up inside of me. And so I really strayed away from
movies and stories that had to do with kids being abducted, you
know, and and the dad then going on this murderous rampage, uh,
which seems relatively justified in light of the way that these horrible
stories. How many of you have read or saw the movie The
Shack? So, guess what? I've never read it and I never watched
it. And that's why people would say, "Oh, man. It's the best
thing ever. You need to like read The Shack." And I was
like, "Okay, I've heard people describe what's going on with the Shack."
And I'm like, "That's not safe for me to read something like
that." Um, and then I discovered that it was fiction. Uh, it
wasn't actually, no, was it be science fiction? Yeah, it wasn't actually
true story. it was just something that somebody made up. And I
said, "Why would you make that up? Why talk about something like
that if it wasn't really a true story?" So, anyways, that's my
punch. Um,
last, well, it wasn't last week. So, two weeks ago, uh, how
many of you were here when I talked about getting a blood
transfusion and a much healthier understanding of the cross? a much
healthier understanding, biblical understanding, uh, Jewishbased perspective on
this subject matter of Jesus's blood and how it saves us, how
it heals us, how it cleanses us. Um, now I had made
a statement or two in that message that were a bit jolting
for folks that maybe the way that you were raised in church
uh, your your paradigm as far as your understanding of why the
cross works. Why did why did the son of god why did
god incarnate have to come and suffer torture and bleed
and die for me? And how do I reconcile that reality in
my heart to all of my sins being forgiven and absorbed? Okay.
So, if you weren't here two weeks ago, I don't want to
preach that message again. Uh but I I made a statement and
I think I was quoting Eaton Bar uh that the blood was
never about wrath. It was about sanctification, about purification and about life.
And so I I had also made a statement and I've preached
a few messages before about how God's nature is not to punish
us. God is not a punisher. Not saying that God does not
discipline, but often we mistake the discipline of God for punishment. And
so often our our theology or our understanding of God is, how
many of you have ever heard it said something like, "Well, God
has no more wrath because he poured it all out on his
son. He's got no more wrath to put on you because all
of his anger was released onto Jesus." Absolutely. >> I have too because
I was I was raised uh to understand that that's what's going
on in the gospel that when we sin and the brokenness of
the world uh has to have some sort of resolution. It has
to be
uh repaired. It has to be fixed. It has to be paid
off. A a debt towards God is owed and Jesus paid that
debt for me. And if you've been going to church here for
very long, we offer a different, more biblical, more Hebraic uh understanding
of sacrifice and of atonement. Atonement is the word for how you
close this gap between offense and being made whole, being back in
relationship. Um, so anyways, God is a punisher. So, I want to
deal with I felt like I had to circle back around because
one of the responses that I get quite often is we deserve
wrath. How can how can you how can you overlook the wrath
of God in the Bible? And so when we talk about the
wrath of God, especially if we've been raised in a more fundamental
background or you've heard lots of preaching, we immediately go back to
the, "Oh, thank God for Jesus because Jesus took all the wrath
of God." In a way that is true, but I feel like
today is a day I want to talk about the wrath of
God. What what is wrath to begin with? So last week when
I talked about God not being a punisher, the blood of Jesus
that God the father did not torture Jesus. God didn't punish Jesus.
Jesus wasn't being punished. Jesus offered his life as an offering to
flush death out of our system. >> Because life was in the blood
and blood was used as a cleansing agent in ancient Hebrew culture.
They didn't torture the animals.
sacrificial victims, animals in Jesus, uh weren't satisfying an angry god by
him feeling better because something suffered. That that's not God at all.
That is not the God we serve. So, we need to take
a hard look at the issue of wrath because I get asked
about, well, what about wrath? We deserve wrath, don't we? And uh
it's it's it's not one that I have found easy to have
a conversation about. So we're going to uh dive in here. But
before we talk about wrath or God's wrath, I have a few
questions for us to consider. And this is all in the context
of us becoming an emotionally healthy church. Because part of our transformation
into the image of Jesus is dealing with all of the hurt
and the pain and really how we react and respond to uh
problems and issues and hurtful things and offenses in life. [clears throat] So
here's a few questions. Should we justify violence of any kind?
How about in self-defense?
Can you justify doing violence? If someone kicks in your door and
they're trying to murder your family, can you justify doing violence to
stop that act? >> That's a good answer.
At at what scale could you consider things to be violent? I
I personally don't like a cockroach in my house. I will put
an end to that life immediately.
>> Yes. My my mother my mother used to like oh don't kill
it and pick up bugs and put them outside, you know. I
I I just Yeah. Anyways,
against who or what and at what threat level do we justify?
Well, that is a justified bit of violence. How do we as
Christians process our own wrath? I would like to say that everyone
experiences wrath.
Um, I was thinking about it and wrath is like this most
visceral reaction to death and evil. It's it's what happens inside of
us when something very wrong happens to someone we love.
I remember when uh when COVID happened, I I got a reputation
um I think even around the world, which is funny, but uh
through the catch the fire network of being the co kid. It
wasn't really the reputation that I wanted. A lot a lot of
I know, right? A a lot of the um uh catch the
fire leaders are known for their revival meetings. Uh you know, one
guy carries this gift of the spirit or the other. They know
me as the the co kid. Uh because when the CO outbreak
happened, I think some of you guys may remember um
lost some lost some folks, some uh really good folks. And I
remember something inside of me when I when I learned that Ivormectin
would knock it out >> in like two days. Something something visceral happened
inside of me. I was I was so moved and upset.
And it wasn't that I was upset at anybody in particular. It
was that I I had this burning desire to not let another
person on my watch die. And so some of you were recipients
of that, but I would look on Facebook if somebody was going
through the symptoms that I was aware of because I had been
very sick with COVID. And uh thanking the Lord that we found
a doctor that would prescribe hydroxychloricquin. Got to say that right. uh
because that works too. It's um you know um antiparasitic drugs would
knock it out. And um anyways, I'd get up at three o'clock
in the morning, drive across town, you know, an hour away to
take people because I bought some Ivormectin and uh well, I wasn't
planning on telling this story, but I just remembered this is just
kind of cool. And whether you believe it or not, it really
happened. I had bought a little bottle of farm version >> because at
the boat dealership all the fishermen were like hush hush or kind
of talking about the secret that they were all getting healed of
of COVID like that and uh so I paid attention and I
thought oh my gosh because they had cattle and stuff and I
I thought this is this can't be this can't be real but
it was and so we bought I went to the feed store
or had an employee go to the feed store and buy a small
bottle of ivormectin uh liquid and found out the right dosage and
everything. And um I remember in the first what two or three
weeks the bottle was half empty because it wasn't a very big
bottle. I mean it was like half the size of a water
bottle. Only takes a few drops to heal you of COVID. And
um I remember thinking I've got to get more like putting all
my trust in this drug. And the Lord said to me in
my spirit he said don't buy anymore. I don't want you to
buy anymore. And I thought, "Oh, okay." And for the next what,
year and a half, I think is how long that went on.
I don't know how many hundreds of people came to my house.
People I don't know, neighbors of neighbors of people that I knocking
on my door and I'd set the Ivormectin out. That bottle did
not drop until CO was almost over. And it was still like
until there was no more threat of >> CO
happened. It really happened. Now, like I said, because that isn't super
glamorous and um they they uh the catch the fire network people
in other countries and in Canada, they they did not have the
availability to get that stuff. Um but I was able to connect
them with our doctor here is just across the street and he
was able to write prescriptions to people on the other side of the
world. So people that were dying like going to die. I know
people that died, they went into the hospital, they never came out.
It's true story. It's horrible. It's just wrong. You know, that disease
is wrong. I don't know who to blame for it, but there's
something inside of me still that is just angry. That's a that's
a a righteous thing, a a holy thing. It's a it's actually
how God is. So, this this word wrath in in
the Old Testament, I think we misunderstand. How many of you when
you think of the term wrath, we think of the wrath of
God. We think of fire and brimstone. We think of God's hand
reached out ready to ready to smite. We think about the destruction
of whole people groups, floods, hurricanes, tornadoes, whatever. Well, technically the
word uh is like two letter. I think it's PE um in
Hebrew. Is that right, Alan? And it just means like face, but
it's the implication is like the countenance on someone's face. It's like,
you know, when you hear of something of great evil, how your
countenance changes and your nostrils flare that it it it literally means
like the flaring of the nostrils. It's a it's an emotional response
to evil. It's like um believe it or not, I mean rodents
aren't evil, but I have a I have an emotional response to
the threat to my family of something that could be carrying rabies
running across the floor. I'm going to put that thing down. I
will stop at nothing to make sure that I eliminate the threat
to the family. >> Amen.
Well, we don't like the idea of of wrath. Uh when we
think of God, we think of God as being this benevolent [sighs and gasps]
teddy bear of a dad. And it's not a bad way to
see him. We like love. We like grace. We like forgiveness because
wrath sounds dangerous and primitive and out of step with God's character.
But here's the irony. We all experience wrath. It's just a an
emotional response to evil. So, I want to talk about what do
we do with it? How how many of you when you hear
of stories of like human trafficking? What does that do inside of
you? I remember when people started talking about it, the first time
I heard of it was like 2015, 14, 15 where churches were
starting to do something about it. And I was I was clueless.
I didn't know that was a thing. It's very inconvenient to think
about that there are people that are being traded that are slaves
today. How about racism? Have you ever witnessed somebody being the on
the wrong end of some racism? Maybe you have been on the
wrong end of racism. Something something inside of us is like that
ain't right. How about child abuse?
Child abuse for me as a one that was an abused child
even as a child I remember being like this is not right.
I knowing that it was not right you know ex extreme punishment
for trivial things. How about war? We should get a pit in
our stomach and when we see people blowing each other to smitherines
absolute destruction of people's lives. betrayal. Maybe you've been betrayed.
That's probably a little more close to home. If someone's ever betrayed
you, betrayed your trust, there's something that rises up inside of you.
So the question is, how does love manifest in our heart when
those that we love are harmed or threatened? What do you feel?
Just being honest. You're not indifferent. Especially if you have kids or
brothers or sisters and maybe even your parents.
When something horrible happens to them, something unjust, you're not indifferent. You're
not like, "Oh, well, God will work it out in the end."
Oh, you're angry, are we not?
>> And it's okay because love without anger isn't actually love.
A father who never becomes angry when someone's abusing their child really
doesn't love his kid very much, does he?
So, if we expect uh human love to oppose evil, how much
more would a perfectly loving God oppose evil?
So, maybe wrath isn't an emotional problem that God has. Maybe wrath
is his holy love confronting evil.
Matter of fact, I'd say this that God's wrath is not the
opposite of his love. It's the expression of his love against everything
that destroys the people he loves.
>> God's wrath is not the opposite of I'm going to say it
again, not the opposite of love. It's the expression of his love
against everything that destroys the people that he loves.
So that was my intro.
When we talk about God's wrath, we need to understand that God's
wrath actually flows out of love. It's not the opposite of love.
It's in opposition to the things
that hurt his people because of love. Exodus 32 through34 is an
interesting
uh chunk of scripture.
Exodus 32 through34. You'll remember the story. The children of Israel are
delivered from the Egyptians out of slavery and they walk through the
Red Sea and all of their enemies are drowned in the waters
there. They get on the other side and they camp camp at
Mount Si. And uh the Lord says, "Get ready because I'm going
to do something special." This is the a God that covenants with
his people, that has married his people, that has chosen to be
their God exclusively, and they will be his people exclusively. And Moses,
he's called forward to lead them through the wilderness into the promised
land. His his heart's desire is always, I am taking you to
a place where you will be incredibly blessed, where you have more
than enough. We have everything you need, where you can exercise and
live out this culture of living with me in peace. Only you
need to become like me. And so he gives Moses the commandments
and Moses goes up on the mountain and while he's etching out
or actually the finger of God is etching out in stone uh
the Ten Commandments or the charter so to speak of their covenant.
the the children of Israel get uh I don't know if it was
bored or if they get uh antsy or whatever, but they're like,
"Where's this Moses guy that's supposed to lead us?" Impatient, maybe a
right word. Impatient, where's he at? Aaron, we want to worship Yahweh
who led us out of slavery. Make make gods for us so
that we can worship him. They they want to get the show
on the road. They want to get this thing wrapped up. And
you know the story. Uh Aaron says that well take all the
earrings and stuff off and he threw it in the fire and
out came a a calf.
>> Just rolled right out of just jumped right out of the fire
according to Aaron. You know that was his story. So, while Moses
is up there getting the the words from heaven straight from the
finger of God and spending time with Yahweh face to face, uh
talking about the the this amazing covenant that he's going to make
is having embraced these people through love and marrying these people. Well,
they were down there doing the opposite, breaking the whole thing up.
So, of course, Moses comes down and smashes the covenant. and but
through Exodus 32 through34, if you'll remember, God's visceral reaction to what
was going on there um was was wrath, right? He was angry.
He was mad. I don't know about you, but if you just
married somebody and uh you know, you had to go on a
a I don't know, extended work weekend or something and and you
come back and they're partying with somebody else, I mean, you probably
experience something very close to what I'm talking about. This visceral reaction
inside to I'm I'm offended, like deeply offended.
But if you'll remember, God We can we get into Exodus 34
and we are privy to and I I love that God is
an emotional God and he's not afraid to share that. And I
think it's incredible that the way that the book is written is
that God kind of discloses himself and he's not hiding the fact
that he's having this discussion about how he feels. He's this is
just how he feels. I'm ready to just wipe them all out.
I'll tell you what, Moses. Let's just start over with you. I'll
just start over with you. We'll just get this thing over with.
And And Moses hits his knees and he says, "Please don't do
that. Please don't do that. Remember the fathers. Remember your promises. Remember
what is Egypt going to think.
Remember your loving kindness, oh God?" He appeals to a different side.
He appeals to his love. It was the actual love of God
that was angry because of love. Anyways, and
the Lord then rather than giving them up because he was about
to blow up this covenant and say, "All right, no more covenant."
But he does not. What does the Lord do? He says, "Okay,
I'm going to I tell you what, I'm going to go with
you. Actually, there's a little back and forth. I'm going to send
my angel. I'm going to stay back a little bit because if
they do this again, it it could get ugly. I mean, I
could Y'all realize that, right? Like the Lord like loved them enough
to say, "But we need to put some distance because they do
that again and this could get ugly." And Moses, that's that's where
Moses says, "No, look, I don't want to go if you won't
go with me. You say that you chose me. You say that
you know me. You say that you handpicked me, that you're going
to deliver me. I don't even I don't even know what you
look like. Show me your face. Lord's like, "Oh, you don't want
to see this face. I I can't show you my face. You
can't live if you see my face." There's something so expressive about
the face of God that it's probably a good thing that we
haven't seen his face other than the face of Jesus.
He says, "But I'll tell you what I'll do. I'll walk by
you and all my goodness will go by you and you'll see
who I really am." And this is this is where he reveals
who he really is here in Exodus 34. Read it with me.
Now the Lord descended in a cloud and stood with him there
and proclaimed the name of the Lord. And the Lord passed before
him and proclaimed, "The Lord, the Lord God, merciful and gracious, long-suffering
and abounding in goodness and truth, keeping mercy for thousands, forgiving iniquity
and transgression and sin, by no means clearing the guilty."
You know what was so upsetting to the Lord was that they
created a god and called it Yahweh.
That they fashioned an image. It wasn't that they thought they were
worshiping another god. Is that they chose to decide how to worship
him and what he was going to look like. Over and over
and over again. The problem that God had when he'd say they've
played the harlot. Y'all ever read that in the Old Testament? How
did they do that?
Worshiping some other god. It's character assassination. He did not want to
be associated with. And it wasn't about like fingers and toes and
eyes and horns and things like that. It was about his character
and his nature. Him setting the record straight here is to say
you got to understand who I am. I am not like the
other gods as if they were even gods as we know they
are rebellious Elohim, rebellious spirit beings that
people worshiped as gods. But they as being the gods of the
other nations would do things like demand blood. They were the ones
that got angry that their people were associated with fear. If they
did something wrong, then the God would retaliate. Yahweh did not want
to be associated in that way at all. And yet at the
same time, he experiences anger and he does something about it. He
will by no means clear the guilty. You're like, "Well, that doesn't
sound great. that that still has an awful ring to it. Well,
let's take a look.
According to this passage of scripture, God introduces himself as compassionate,
gracious, slow to anger, and abounding in steadfast love. Hallelujah.
>> It's not that he doesn't get angry or experience the emotion of
anger. It's just what does he do with it?
We know that he's perfectly righteous and that he could in his
own right and he's sovereign and holy and all that stuff. He
could do whatever he wants to.
But because he's a god of love, he does the right stuff
with his anger. So wrath isn't God's first instinct. Love is. His
anger is slow. His mercy is abundant. And his justice is absolutely
necessary for him to do something about it. He can't just do
nothing and let it let it go by.
So I I don't know how how many of you uh know who
or love Tim Mackey know who he is. >> Couple of you. Tim
Tim Mackey um he's a a great theologian scholar of our day
and also a prolific Bible teacher and he has um a um
I don't know if it's a program what to call it but
anyways he he he he started what they call Bible project. Who knows
what Bible project is? Bible project is fantastic where they tell the
story of the Bible and themes in the Bible through uh illustrations
as they unpack it super simple taking very complex truth and making
it simple. Uh anyways the Tim Mackey's perspective is this that throughout
scripture wrath is often portrayed as God allowing humanity to experience the
natural consequences of rejecting his life. This is a better way of
understanding this. I even think that when I was discipled, this is
the way that John Collins taught us. Um, I'm going to say
that again. Throughout scripture, and and as we talk more about it,
you'll recall that this is true. Wrath is often portrayed as God
allowing humanity to experience the natural consequences of rejecting his life.
If you think about Kings and Chronicles and even 1 and 2
Samuel, that whole history of Israel and its heyday and also in
its uh constant crisis, every everything kind of revolved around that.
They would choose to intermar. And it wasn't that intermarriage was wrong
in itself. It was that other nations that were surrounding them belong
to they were married to these other gods. And so when they
would take another family in, they would have to then worship their
gods. And by virtue, that would be like spiritual adultery. And all
of the things that they practiced because the other gods were very
I don't I don't know the right words, but they were just
awful and had a lot of awful ways in which they practiced
sacrificing children. Um, you know, unfaithfulness to spouses, that was out the
window. uh lots of ways that they practiced or worshiped their gods
that were very unhealthy for humanity, unhealthy for a culture where God's
spirit was to dwell.
You we see this in the New Testament in Romans. This is
interesting. It's probably
I don't know in our culture today, Romans 1, it's like we
let's start somewhere around Romans 3. you know, we don't like to
to look at Romans 1, but it's in there. We're talking about
the wrath of God. Romans 1's got the the language of wrath
in it. Uh, so read it with me starting verse 18. For
the wrath of God is revealed. It's revealed from heaven. So Paul
is going to tell us what the wrath of God looks like.
For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness
and unrighteousness of men who suppress the truth in unrighteousness because what
may be known of God is manifest in them. For God has
shown it to them. And you guys probably know the rest. It
starts talking about worshiping the uh creation instead of the creator. And
specifically this is talking about sexuality, believe it or not. uh and
how we steward or how historically people have stewarded their bodies. If
we jump down to verse 24, I just want to point out,
read it with me. Therefore, God also gave them up to uncleanness
in the lust of their hearts to dishonor their bodies among themselves,
who exchanged the truth of God for the lie, and worshiped and
served the creature rather than the creator who is blessed forever. Amen.
For this reason, God gave them up to vile passions. So in
verse 18, it says, "The wrath of God is revealed from heaven
against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of men." And here's the definition is
that his wrath looks like giving us over to our own ways.
Romans 1 repeats this cycle like God gave them over. So sometimes
or I would say that most often the wrath of God doesn't
look like fire and brimstone or lightning bolts, but it's actually God
saying, "If this is what you insist on, I'm going to let
you have it." Sin eventually becomes its own punishment.
I know. I wish I didn't know, but I do know. There's
nothing worse than that feeling when um and God is slow to
anger, rich in mercy, abundant in mercy, longsuffering towards us. And it
is amazing to me how long he'll let us go before he
says, "Hey, look, you really want that? Then I'll just let you
have it." because the fruit of that is going to eat you
alive. So most of when you're reading the prophets in the Old
Testament, if you understand that that's what's going on, it makes it
so much more clear that it's this constant, especially like Isaiah and
Jeremiah, it's this it's this constant plea through the prophet to the
people of Israel, return to me, return to me, return to me.
If you not not do not return to me, it's going to
get ugly because you are going to reap what you sow. it's
going to come back on you. And it's not like God is
up there pulling the strings making that happen. No, he's already set
things in motion. Rather, instead, God is holding back, always holding back
things from getting to us. The last thing we want to do
is have him remove his hand and say, "If you insist, then
have it already." But you'll recall the pattern in scripture is that
then he brings him back once they've had a good taste of
it and they cry out to him. Brings him back. Brings him
back. Brings him back. I'm so thankful that that is the nature
and character of our God. >> Have you ever had a belly full
of your own folly? >> Absolutely. >> Where you're like, I can this is
horrible. >> This is punishment. This is hell.
Wrath is God giving humanity what it chooses. Romans 1. So Paul
doesn't describe wrath primarily as fire. He describes it as disintegration.
Notice the pattern. If we had read that whole passage, people reject
God. God gives them over. Life unravels. Relationships fracture,
communities collapse,
hearts harden.
If you think about it, this echoes the exile story, as I
brought up. It's like most of that promised land forward in the
Old Testament is is that story over and over again, especially the
one to Babylon. Humanity chooses life apart from God. God honors that
decision.
I had um yeah, I found that out firsthand. I I grew
up in a Christian home and knew all the Christian stuff basically,
but not like heart didn't really know it with my heart. I
just knew details that I'd heard and uh went through a horrible
season with uh my parents divorce and everything coming off the wheels.
You guys know I've talked about it. Uh, but I remember when
I hardened my heart and I decided to just go crazy and
do lots of things that were um just dangerous, harmful to myself,
harmful to others, harmful to God, hurtful to God, I should say.
And I remember having a having a dream once and um I've
never even talked about this before, but the the dream was this
that like I was in heaven already and angels that had their
faces covered wouldn't even look at me like open the gates and
then I freefeld and I was free falling to the earth and
as I got closer I just heard all this yelling and like
a mosh pit just ah a and all these hands and I
just fell right into the chaos and uh I thought well that
was a bit extreme but that's how either that was the Lord
speaking to me or me processing what was going on because I
did I I u just walked away from church I walked away
from uh really anybody that loved me and just decided to go
crazy for a while and um I can say that the Lord
at some point stopped
protecting me from my own decisions. They let me start feeling that
weight of decisions I was making. And um that got my attention
immediately. That got my attention immediately. Sitting in a jail cell. I
was like
for writing in wet concrete [laughter] of all things. Writing in wet
concrete. Went to jail for that. had my attention.
So Anti Wright's perspective is this about Romans 1.
Anti Wright, as you know, we talk about him a lot and
his perspectives, but he he's saying that Romans is Paul is retelling
Israel's story. And I love that. Uh, of course, that's kind of
a a higher learning position to take as you begin to study
at another level. Paul is actually retelling Israel's story. And wrath is
covenantal language. So if if you were not in covenant with God,
I'm not saying that wrath doesn't exist, but it's not the same
thing. This is something that lovers would experience, and it is the
consequence of idolatry.
And throughout Israel's history, God allows idols and their archons and the
powers that are behind those idols to become tyrants. Sin enslaves. Wrath
exposes that slavery. God's judgment isn't arbitrary. It's the
moral fabric of creation responding to rebellion.
Deep thoughts. Deep thoughts. All right, second point. So God wrath is
God giving humanity what it chooses. And the second point is that
God does not delight in wrath. That like there's nothing about it
that God likes. Ezekiel 18:23.
Um, do we have that one?
Maybe I didn't make a slide for Ezekiel 18:23, but it says
this. Do I have any pleasure at all in that the wicked
should die, says the Lord God, and not that he should turn
from his ways and live?
That that chapter there in Ezekiel 18, it's like God reasoning with
Israel like you say I'm unjust, but you're the one that's actually
unjust. like I I'm I have no desire for anybody to die,
not even wicked people. I desire that wicked people would turn and
he starts talking about if the wicked would turn and amend their
ways, then I will absolutely embrace them and heal them and bless
them. And conversely, if righteous people decide to then do wickedness, they
will suffer the consequences of it. But that's not because God enjoys
that. He doesn't like that at all. He is the most long-suffering
person that you could ever imagine. I mean, I've I've tried to
really I've tried to think about the heart of God, what it
must be like for him to actually bear because he doesn't just
blow it off like, "Oh, well, you know, oh, yep, Jesus, I
did that to him. Okay, we're good." No, the heart of God
is grieved over our pain. It's grieved over our evil. He's grieved
over our tragedies. Verse 32, you jump down. He says, 'For I
have no I have no pleasure in the death of one who
dies, says the Lord God. Therefore, turn and live.
God's desire is always restoration. >> Amen.
>> Huh? >> Every warning in scripture is an invitation. I I remember um
shortly after I received Christ
when the Lord dealt with my own like anger issue. Like I
didn't
I didn't realize that it was what it was until I had
the Holy Spirit. But for a couple years there, I I could
get super angry. I I don't know if anybody has ever had this
or maybe you've heard me talk about this or not, but I
I remember getting super angry and I got in a bunch of
fights, too. And I got chip teeth. Chip teeth to prove it.
But um I remember when I would when I would get angry,
I could relate to The Incredible Hulk because something would come over
me that was almost superhuman. And adrenaline's probably got something to do
with that. But um you know, I'd have a fight and and
then when I'd come down the next day physically I would be
sick
like and I didn't really pick up on that until after I
had received Jesus and everything was great and I got in a
fight with my brother and that happened to me. The Rage Monster
came out and I was like, "Whoa, that is not from God."
I was like, "This is not God at all." And and I
remember telling the Lord like, he did so much when he when
he remember I told you two weeks ago about the transfusion of
life where the blood of Jesus actually purged me and cleansed me
and healed me in so many ways. But I had to discover
that, oh no, there's lots more that God's going to work on.
And anger was like one of the one of the or rage
is a better way is one of the first things that that
he dealt with. And uh I remember that sick horrible feeling like
like down in my bones and my whole body hurt like the
Hulk, you know, when uh Dr. Banner would come back to himself
and he's like, "Oh, needs he needs to be refreshed." Um I
remember telling the Lord, "I never ever ever want to do this
again. God, would you please take this from me?" And he did
right then and there. I have never never experienced that again. The
the rage monster. You know, I have had some anger, but not
like that. Does anybody know what I'm talking about? >> Absolutely. >> Ever experienced
go some guys are like a few of you ladies, but uh
yeah, I mean if if you struggle with that, I can just
tell you right now, you you can totally be delivered to that.
>> Yeah. Anyways, uh Merislav Wolf, I I I love this guy. He's
um one of the theologians that really shifted and changed my life.
But his work exclusion and embrace, he talks about um reconciliation, forgiveness.
He talks about justice a lot. And he definitely talks about h
how do we process this victim being left hanging? Um
subject matter. What what about the wrath of God? What about vengeance
is mine, says the Lord. I will repay. But here's here's Miris
Vulfe. He says, "Many modern people reject divine wrath because they've never
experienced large-scale injustice." And um he comes from uh Croatia,
I think, where the ethnic cleansing was going on with his family.
A lot of his family members were um yeah, I won't even
talk about it, but experienced that ethnic cleansing. He said, "Victims know
better.
If God never judges evil, then evil wins. God has to do
something about it. He's not going to just say, "Oh, it's okay."
Forgiveness without justice becomes indifference.
And I'm I'm thankful to know that that's not what God requires
when he asks us to forgive. It's not no big deal. I've
been violated. No big deal. God's going to fix it. The cross
allows justice and mercy to meet.
God refuses to ignore evil because he overcomes it.
>> What's that? The cross allows justice and mercy to meet.
I I've talked about a story as I was I actually I
opened with this. I just didn't talk much about it. But um
as I was growing in my relationship with the Lord, probably four
or five years in, I started having these dreams of um I
wake up from the dreams and think, "Oh, Jesus, I've been working
so hard to be holy and to be nice to people." And
I'm scaring myself with these dreams. Is this a is this a
sign that I'm really like crazy or something or I'm I'm really
dangerous person? because I was having these dreams where there would be
some perpetrator breaking into my house or coming after my kids and
my family and I would do violence to this perpetrator. And the
problem was the the biggest tension wasn't me doing the violence necessarily.
It was then, uhoh,
I have a corpse on my hands. What am I going to
do with this evidence that I had done violence even though it
was justified? They were hurting my family. And so that was always
the thing like throw them in a ditch, throw them in a
dumpster, you know. And I really I thought I I Lord have
mercy. I'm damaged goods. God, please tell me I'm not going to
do something like that, Lord. And uh I remember going to my
pastor and I told my pastor about it and said I I
got the courage to actually say it out loud and tell him.
And he's like, "Oh no, that's not what that means at all."
He says, "You know, you're experiencing somewhere in your life a uh
darned if you do, darn if you don't situation. You're stuck. You're
trapped. You feel like if you you you're experiencing some injustice somewhere,
and you feel like if you do something about it, you'll be
punished. And I instantly was like, "Oh my gosh, I was getting
messed around at work." And I'm the Christian guy. And I didn't
want to cause a scene or make a stir. But basically, there
was some inequality going on. And I went and told the boss
said, "Hey, you can't do that. I've been here longer. Why are
you giving this guy uh all this preferential treatment? Why don't you just
treat us equal? That's not right." And he said, "Okay." and that
was it. And I never had another dream. Now today, I'm I'm
seeing a much deeper reality that God was at work in me
to really change my foundation and the way I think about this
visceral visceral reaction that I have to injustice and stuff that is
wrong. And the reaction that is appropriate is to honoringly
challenge that injustice
to say something to do something. Not just to oh well doesn't
matter or not to do something crazy and decide to be passive
aggressive towards the people that are responsible but rather to address it.
And that is a really really healthy approach for us to understand.
Ultimately, God will make everything right. God will judge. There is
such a thing as the judgment seat of Christ. But how many
of you know that we don't have to fear that? I'm thinking
of like 1 John 4 there where it talks about uh there
is no fear in love. Perfect love casts out fear. Why? Because
fear involves punishment.
God is not a punisher. He's he he's not looking to pay
back somebody. No. When God expresses wrath, it's actually his love
reaching out to stop things from destroying his people, from destroying those
he loves.
How we doing?
>> Jesus doesn't sing save us from an angry father. And we kind
of covered this two weeks ago, but we need to understand that
Jesus isn't standing there holding dad back because dad's really angry at
something that you did.
This is some of that eaten bar perspective. Instead, what do we
see in scripture? God himself bears wrath.
You can look at John chapter 3, Romans 5, Isaiah 53.
The father isn't against the son. Father, son, and holy spirit, they
all together are rescuing humanity.
The cross reveals that God absorbs evil rather than simply inflicting punishment.
Jesus steps into the consequences of human rebellion.
The judge becomes the judged.
Love pays the cost.
I think about John chapter 3. Right there at the end, there's
a statement that says that those that have not believed on him,
the wrath of God abides on them. That's a hard one to
process, is it not? I mean, in my evangelical American Christian worldview,
it'd be easy for me to walk outside and think, heathens, wrath
of God abides on you. Wrath's coming. You're going to suffer the
wrath of Almighty God. How about Revelation where the angel puts a
sickle in and reaps a harvest and then tramples the the wine
press of the wrath of God.
Oh my goodness.
I think that a lot of a lot of those verses, Paul's
perspective
would have been understood and well known as
nations being conquered by other nations and the devastation that happens when
a a nation that has gone a muck because they can't get
along, right? When when there's no unifi unity, a house divided cannot
stand. This is happens nationally when when nations and I Lord bless
America. Please help us to love one another and be unified again
>> because when a people group are divided, they they just run a
muck and they run a mess and they're weakened. And it's pretty
well understood that because of all that selfishness, because that's what causes
that, I I'm right. No, you're wrong. I'm right. because of all
that selfishness, it just makes you like pray for some stronger nation
that sees the resources that you're sitting on and wants to come
take them. So when Paul often and even in the New Testament
when they're referring to wrath like that, it's that there's a day
of reckoning coming, it's it's framed within this idea of a day
of the Lord or a day of wrath is when everything switches
over. when you finally get nationally the repercussions of not
being able to work it out together, of not being strong enough
to
hold it together as a nation. That's the way that I've seen
wrath used that way.
How many of you know that humanity in general because of our
inability to unify because of our decisions and our attitude of well
no I know better. I want to do it my way. And
what fixes that is our ability to surrender to God and say,
"God, I I have no idea. My way is terrible. I I
just publicly acknowledge that right now." Like my my way without the
Lord is terrible. I'm my own worst enemy. I will absolutely make
a mess out of this deal. Have sometimes do still
humanity as a whole in that attitude towards God. No thanks. That
Romans 1 was talking about no thanks. We've got it all figured
out. They became wise in their own eyes.
decided how it's going to be in that inability because when you're
doing that and everybody's doing that, nobody's unified. Nobody's got anything to.
If we have any unity, it's all it's because well, what you've
got to offer serves my purpose. That's why when we believe in
Jesus in the person of Jesus and he comes to give his
life away and we understand that in giving ourselves away and being
in covenant with one another and with God that that brings life
and health and unity that cannot be broken. That's why
wrath is not for you. And we could say that wrath in
that sense is for those that have not received Jesus. Does that
make sense? Is that slightly different than the way that I proposed
or the way that you grew up with evangelical American Christianity?
It's not just a decision. Oh, okay. Well, I said the prayer
and culturally I go to church sometimes and I say, "Yep, I
believe in Jesus. Therefore, the wrath of God does not abide on
me. because Jesus took all the wrath from God. No,
it looks more like I have received Christ. He's breathed the spirit
of life into my lungs. I've become one with him and everything
about his life has been inherited. I've surrendered my desire and my
will to do everything the way I want. And now I'm living
for this great plan that he's laid out.
Wrath is not the final goal. How many of you know that
this plan that God has at work is not just to wipe
everything out? Revelation 21 ends with no tears, no death, no curse,
no mourning, no evil.
God's final word is not wrath. It's new creation.
It's a promise of a whole new world that he's creating even
now in you and through you and for you.
Wrath clears the way. I'm sorry. Wrath clears away evil so love
can flourish forever.
All right, I'm wrapping up.
Tim Mackey's perspective is that the Bible begins in a garden and
it ends in a city. The whole story is moving toward this
renewed creation. Wrath removes everything that corrupts God's good world because love
is your destination.
So when we talk about the gospel, the invitation, all the warnings
being an invitation, it's not escape hell, it's come home.
Turn from the idols that are destroying you. Receive the God who
loves you enough to oppose everything that's killing you and ruining your
life.
Repentance isn't punishment. It's a rescue.
Matthew.
Matthew in here.
So, here's a few questions for us to answer as we're wrapping
up. Where am I resisting God's loving rule?
Where am I still
content to make my own decisions and think that my way is
better.
What would it look like if I could let go of that?
Do I trust that he's good enough
to direct my steps, rewrite my story?
Are there any consequences in my life? Repercussions of my decisions that
I'm just calling bad luck or
the enemy that may actually be the Lord just letting you have
what you chose. That's actually just an invitation to come back to
his heart.
I remember when I came back to the Lord,
I tried a couple times to do it on my own to
give up a few things and the Lord said, "No, I want
all of you. I don't just want part of you. I want
all of you."
It's like with Lauren. I want all of her. I want to
be her husband on Tuesday and Wednesday. I want to be her
husband every day of the week. God wants all of us. We
can trust him with all of us.
The last question is, am I representing him well? Am I [snorts]
reflecting his heart?
Have I learned how to hate evil without hating people?
>> Can I uh oppose injustice while loving my enemies?
That's what he wants to do in his church.
Only the spirit of God living inside of us.
The nature of Christ being developed in us could do this stuff.
>> Only a surrender to him [snorts] produces that kind of a life.
[snorts]
Just imagine this. Imagine the world with [snorts] no abuse,
no violence, no addiction,
no death,
no corruption,
no guilt, no shame,
no burden.
[snorts] We all long for this world.
This is what's been promised to us.
The only way God brings it about is by finally dealing with
evil.
That's wrath. Not love's opposite, but love's refusal to surrender.
>> [snorts] [sighs] >> Let's take communion as we close. Let's take communion.
Probably should have had us do that already, but let's go. Let's
go for it.
Have a couple of our
leader service.
>> [snorts]
>> Thank you. [snorts]
Aren't you grateful that God gave us
just a prophetic enactment, a tactile way for us to
[sighs] step back into covenant to renew and refresh, rehearse the
covenant Jesus made with us. Not just to remember, but to kind
of re-mbod.
This this is this moment is for you, church. It's for us
together, but it's for you,
Lord. Thank you for what you've done,
Lord. We thank you for coming and exhibiting perfect righteousness,
perfect love.
Lord, I thank you that you didn't just do it like Superman.
You did it in human frailty.
Flesh and blood and bone just like us, God. Lord, I thank
you that you are an emotional God. that you feel everything that
we feel. Lord, there isn't anything that we've experienced no pain, no
trauma,
no discouragement,
even anger that we don't that we feel. [snorts]
You are intimately acquainted with our grief.
Lord, we thank you for taking all of that
upon yourself,
bearing our guilt and our shame, our sicknesses and our diseases, God,
putting it to death, Lord.
Thank you. We just received your body.
Take the bread with me.
[snorts]
Today, as we share this cup, as I spoke a few weeks
ago about a transfusion of life, I want you to understand that
the very life of God, the life of Jesus
is for you to heal you, to cleanse you, to purify you,
to cleanse even your conscience,
to make you whole.
Even the smell of smoke, the
remains of trauma and death, all of that is dealt with in
the blood of Jesus. So Jesus, we thank you for your life.
Lord, we gladly accept your life.
We are your people. We are your hands and feet. Take the
cup with me.
So, if you've been watching online, God bless you.
Pray you have a wonderful week. You guys, if we can stand
with you in prayer, pray for you to all. If if God's
at work in your life, I would be so excited to hear
about it. If this if you've had a a visual reaction to
this sermon, please feel free. I' I would genuinely love to
counsel you to to talk about it. I' I'd like to know.
God bless you guys. Have a great week.